<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<sect1 id="gallery-remote.using">
 <title>Using Gallery Remote</title>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.platforms">
  <title>Can I run Gallery Remote on platforms for which there is no installer?</title>
  <para>
   Yes, maybe. Gallery Remote was written in Java. 
   If you have Java 1.3 or later installed on your machine, you may be able to run the app with the command:
   java -cp GalleryRemote.jar com.gallery.GalleryRemote.GalleryRemote
   assuming you are in the same directory as the GalleryRemote.jar file.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.preferences">
  <title>Preferences</title>
   <para>
   Even though there is now a Preferences dialog, the preference files can still be edited. You should not 
   modify the defaults.properties file, but you should read it to understand what each preference does. 
   Then, you can edit the GalleryRemote.properties (it is created the first time GR is run) and add or replace the preferences you want to change.

   The preferences files used to be stored in the same directory as the GalleryRemote executable, 
   and has been moved (and renamed) to the current user's home directory.
    
   On recent versions of Windows, this is the Documents and Settings/username directory in the boot partition. 
   When you upgrade from versions older than 1.0b6, you will lose your current preferences unless you copy the previously used remote.properties to 
   home directory/.GalleryRemote/GalleryRemote.properties.
   </para>
 </sect2>             
 
 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.logging">
  <title>Logging</title>
   <para>
   If you encounter a problem, the logging system may be some help, and we will definitely request it if you ask for support.
   By default, GR writes most log information to the file log.txt in the directory where you installed GR. 
   If you want to see more detailed information there, you can add the following lines to your GalleryRemote.properties file:

  logLevel=3
  toSysOut=true

  If you also change your InstallAnywhere launcher file Gallery Remote.lax to set:

  lax.stdout.redirect=console

  you will see the log as it unfolds in the console...
   <note>
    <para>
    Caution: Be careful before posting your log to forums or sending it to anyone: your password is printed in clear text in several places.
    </para>
   </note>
  
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
